جُوَيْق أو الخضراء قرية جبلية جميلة بنيت على السفح الجنوبي
لهضبة كلسية متوسطة الارتفاع
Jweq or Al-Khadra is a beautiful mountain village built on
the southern slope of a medium-height calcareous plateau,
شمال غرب مدينة عفرين في ريف حلب الشمالي بثمانية كيلومترات
وتتبع لها.
eight kilometers northwest of the city of Afrin in the
northern countryside of Aleppo, and belongs to it.
كما أنها تبعد عن مدينة حلب سبعين كيلومترا باتجاه الشمال
الغربي.
It is also 70 kilometers northwest of the city of Aleppo.
يقسمها إلى قسمين واد كان يمر فيه جدول مائي من نبع ماء دائم
الجريان في وسط القرية.
It is divided into two parts by a valley through which a
stream of water used to flow from a permanently flowing
spring in the center of the village.
كما أن الوادي الكبير القادم من قرية داركير يمر جنوبها
Also, the large valley coming from the village of Dargir
passes south of it,
وإلى الشرق منها يقع نبع ماء إلى جانب موقع عين ديبا الأثري.
and to the east of it lies a water spring next to the
archaeological site of Ain Diba.
سكانها الأصليون يشكلون لوحة سورية فريدة مكونة من الكرد
والعرب والتركمان السوريين.
Its original inhabitants form a unique Syrian mosaic made up
of Kurds, Arabs, and Syrian Turkmen.
يعتمد سكانها بالأصل على الزيتون والفواكه والحبوب وعلى تربية
الحيوانات.
Its inhabitants originally rely on olives, fruits, grains,
and animal husbandry.
نسبة كبيرة من أبنائها هاجر إلى أوروبا للعمل والدراسة.
A large percentage of its people immigrated to Europe for
work and study.
هناك أكثر من ثلاثمئة عائلة نازحة من مختلف المناطق السورية
إليها.
There are more than 300 displaced families from various
Syrian regions in the village.
يوجد في القرية مدرستين ابتدائية وإعدادية.
There are two schools in the village, a primary and a middle
school.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام أهلا أخي.
And upon you be peace, welcome brother.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
شلونك؟
Welcome.
How are you?
نتعرف عليك؟
Praise be to God, how are you?
Can we get to know you?
الحمد لله. مراد حجي حسين ابن جميل نعسو.
Praise be to God. Murad Haji Hussein, son of Jamil Na'so.
أهلا وسهلا من هون من جويق؟
Welcome, are you from here, from Jweq?
إيه من جويق أخي.
Yes, from Jweq, brother.
نعم. خلينا نحكي لك شوي عن جويق، احكي لي عن يعني طبيعة الناس
هون.
Yes. Let's talk a little about Jweq. Tell me about the
nature of the people here.
طبيعة الناس، ناس عندهم في ناس يعني مواسم كالزيتون والقمح
وهذا يعني...
The nature of the people, people have, there are people, I
mean, crops like olives and wheat, and this, I mean...
أهل الضيعة بيعتمدوا على هالشي؟
The village people rely on this?
في ناس درسوا، راحوا على المدن وتوظفوا، والبقية بالضيعة ناس
بيشتغلوا بأراضيهم بزيتوناتهم.
Some people studied, went to the cities and got employed,
and the rest in the village are people who work in their
lands and olive groves.
يعني مجتمع زراعي؟
So it's an agricultural society?
مجتمع زراعي، إيه والله.
An agricultural society, yes indeed.
لكن مدني، شلون الدراسة عندكم؟
But civil, how is education here?
الدراسة والله في ناس درسوا الطب، في ناس درسوا الهندسة، في
ناس يعني حسب التكوينات الدراسية.
Education, well, some people studied medicine, some studied
engineering, some... I mean, depending on the educational
backgrounds.
يعني في... في تعليم كويس؟
I mean, there is... there is good education?
إيه تعليم بالضيعة بس حدا اللي دارس ما بيبرك بالضيعة.
Yes, education in the village, but whoever is educated
doesn't stay in the village.
لأنه ما في شغل بالضيعة؟
Because there is no work in the village?
ما في شغل.
There is no work.
إيه بيبرك بالمدينة، بيعيش ولاده هو على المدينة.
Yes, he stays in the city, he raises his kids in the city.
أما باقي الضيعة نصها ساكنين كما ترون الضيعة يعني مأهلة
بالسكان.
As for the rest of the village, half of them are residents,
as you can see, the village is, I mean, populated.
سكان نعم. هلق السكان اللي هون في أكراد وفي عرب وفي تركمان.
Residents, yes. Now the residents here, there are Kurds,
Arabs, and Turkmen.
شلون طبيعة العلاقة بيناتهم؟
How is the nature of the relationship between them?
علاقة أخوية أخي.
A brotherly relationship, brother.
شلون يعني؟
How so?
يعني تبادل زيارات، مثلا سهرات، بيبركوا عند بعض، هذا بيشتكي
عن حاله لهاد، كأخي يعني باركين عند بعض.
I mean exchanging visits, for example, evening gatherings,
they sit with each other, this one complains about his
situation to that one, like brothers, I mean, sitting with
each other.
آه يعني بيتشاركوا في الأعياد في الأفراح في المناسبات؟
Ah, so they share in holidays, weddings, and occasions?
في كل المناسبات. في كل المناسبات.
In all occasions. In all occasions.
نعم. اعتماد الناس هون على إيش؟
Yes. What do people rely on here?
أول شيء على الزراعة.
First of all, on agriculture.
زراعة.
Agriculture.
إيه نعم.
Yes, indeed.
نعم. أخي، ايش بيزرعوا؟
Yes. Brother, what do they plant?
أكثر شيء زيتون.
Mostly olives.
زيتون.
Olives.
إيه في بالدشت أراضي مو مزروعة هدول ناس بيزرعوها إيش سقي،
بيزرعوا خضرة، بيزرعوا...
Yes, in the plains, there are unplanted lands, these people
plant them with, what do you call it, irrigation, they plant
vegetables, they plant...
ناس... أشجار مثمرة.
People... fruit trees.
يعني أشجار مثمرة. إيه كالرمان والفواكه.
I mean, fruit trees. Yes, like pomegranates and fruits.
بس باقي الإيش؟ الأراضي قمح وهذا العالم الناس بياكلوا من
رزقهم وعملهم.
But the rest of the, what? The lands, wheat and this, the
world, people eat from their livelihood and their work.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
أهلا وسهلا. أنا بشكر حلب اليوم وأهلا وسهلا فيكم وتشرفونا
أهلا وسهلا أهين.
Welcome. I thank Halab Al-Youm, and welcome to you, you
honor us, welcome, welcome.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy and blessings of God be upon you.
أهلا بك.
Welcome.
يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
شلونك؟
May God greet you.
How are you?
حياك الله، أهلا شباب.
May God greet you, welcome guys.
نتعرف عليك هون.
Let's get to know you here.
عبد الجليل العلي من ريف حماة السهل الغاب.
Abdul Jalil Al-Ali from the countryside of Hama, Al-Ghab
Plain.
أهلا وسهلا فيك.
Welcome to you.
خالد حسن من ريف حماة سهل الغاب.
Khalid Hassan from the countryside of Hama, Al-Ghab Plain.
أهلا وسهلا فيكم.
Welcome to you.
احكوا لي يعني يعني الشيء المميز بهالضيعة، قد إيش صار لكم هون
أنتم؟
Tell me, I mean, the special thing about this village. How
long have you been here?
تقريبا ما يقارب السنة... سنتين، سنتين وشهر تقريبا، سنتين
وشهر.
Approximately around a year... two years, two years and a
month almost, two years and a month.
مهجرين لهون.
Displaced here.
إيش هو الشيء الملفت للنظر بهالضيعة بجويق؟
Displaced.
What is the eye-catching thing about this village, Jweq?
الملفت للنظر بهالضيعة إنه الناس متفقة مع بعضها.
The eye-catching thing in this village is that the people
get along with each other.
يعني كالمقيمين أو المهجرين، يعني موجودة بيناتهم المحبة.
I mean, whether residents or displaced, I mean, love exists
between them.
بـ... متفقين بجميع النواحي بنشاركهم بـ... بنشاركهم عزاءهم
وفرحهم وبيشاركونا عزاءنا وفرحنا.
By... agreeing in all aspects, we share with them... we
share their sorrow and joy, and they share our sorrow and
joy.
تمام. في صار زواجات بين هأهل القرية والمهجرين؟
Great. Have there been marriages between the village people
and the displaced?
صار زواجات. نسبة قليلة يعني لحد الآن.
Marriages happened. A small percentage, I mean, so far.
في زواجات.
There are marriages.
إيش هو أهم شيء المشترك الآن بيناتكم؟
What is the most important common thing between you now?
الأهم شيء المشترك الاتفاق، متفقين مع بعض، المحبة موجودة.
The most important common thing is agreement, agreeing with
each other, love is present.
يعني... يعني ما بنريد المضرة لهم ولا هن...
I mean... I mean we don't wish harm upon them nor do they...
في أعمال مشتركة بيناتكم؟
Are there joint works between you?
طبعا الأعمال المشتركة... إحنا أول ما جينا نزحنا لهون في كثير
مزروعات ما بيعرفوا فيها.
Of course, joint works... When we first came and were
displaced here, there were many crops they didn't know
about.
يعني صرنا نزرع يعني معاهم نشارك، علمناهم على كثير مزروعات.
I mean, we started planting, I mean, with them,
participating. We taught them about many crops.
مثل إيش؟
Like what?
مثل حبة البركة ما كانوا يزرعوها.
Like black seed, they didn't use to plant it.
بين الزيتون؟
Between the olives?
إيه. العصفر ما كانوا يزرعوه، في عندهم أراضي سليخ يعني سليخ
بدون زيتون.
Yes. Safflower, they didn't use to plant it. They have bare
lands, I mean bare without olives.
يعني تعلموا زراعتها، الخضراوات وكذا...
I mean, they learned how to plant them, vegetables and so
on...
حلو. كثير حلو.
Nice. Very nice.
بتضيف شيء؟
Do you want to add anything?
نعم. كنت شارد شوي.
Yes. You were a bit distracted.
إيه.
Yes.
شو بدك تضيف أنت؟ شو تعلمت من أهل جويق؟
What do you want to add? What did you learn from the people
of Jweq?
يعني تعلمنا طبعا العادات، عاداتهم، عندهم عادات يعني حلوة،
مختلفة عن عاداتنا شوي.
I mean, we learned, of course, the customs, their customs,
they have, I mean, nice customs, slightly different from our
customs.
مثل إيش؟
Like what?
مثل بأفراحهم يعني بيحبوا يشاركوا الجميع.
Like in their weddings, I mean, they like to include
everyone.
أحيانا نحن في عندنا عادات إنه الفرح مثلا بيكون خاص بأهل
العرس.
Sometimes we have customs that the wedding, for example, is
private to the family of the wedding.
أما بالنسبة للأكراد لأ عامة، مختلط، محشرانية كثير جدا.
But for the Kurds, no, it's public, mixed, very outgoing.
يا سيدي الله هيك يديم السعادة ويديم الفرح عليكم.
Sir, may God prolong happiness and prolong joy for you.
اللهم آمين، آمين يا رب العالمين.
Amen, O God, amen, O Lord of the Worlds.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
حياك الله، الله يعافيك أستاذ.
May God greet you, may God give you health, sir.
أهلا وسهلا أستاذ.
Welcome, sir.
المنطقة الواقفين فيها هي وحدة من أقدم وأعرق المناطق الموجودة
في جويق.
The area we are standing in is one of the oldest and most
ancient areas in Jweq.
خلفنا الجامع بمئذنته العريقة وبناءه التاريخي.
Behind us is the mosque with its ancient minaret and
historical building.
وأيضا المعصرة على يميننا، معصرة أيضا قديمة في القرية.
And also the olive press on our right, also an old press in
the village.
وأمامنا الآن هو بيت قديم يسمى بيت عز الدين.
And in front of us now is an old house called Izz al-Din's
house.
عمره أكثر من مئتين وخمسين سنة.
It is more than 250 years old.
رح أدخل معكم لهالبيت لنتعرف على نمط البناء بهالضيعة.
I will go inside this house with you to explore the
architectural style in this village.
هالبيت بيمثل نمط تقليدي من يعني من أنماط البناء المعروفة
كتير في القرية.
This house represents a traditional style of, I mean, the
well-known architectural styles in the village.
معظم بيوت القرية شبيهة بهذا البيت.
Most of the houses in the village are similar to this house.
تفضلوا معانا نتعرف على شكل هالبناء هون.
Please come with us to discover the shape of this building
here.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته، أهلين أستاذ.
And upon you be peace, mercy, and blessings of God, welcome
sir.
شلونك؟
How are you?
تفضلوا تفضلوا أهلا وسهلا أهلا وسهلا أستاذي.
Come in, come in, welcome, welcome, my teacher.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك يا رب الله يسلمك.
May God give you health, may God keep you safe.
أول شيء بدي اتعرف عليك.
First, I want to get to know you.
تفضل، عز الدين عثمان ابن محمد دريعي.
Go ahead, Izz al-Din Othman, son of Muhammad Driei.
يا أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
الله يسلمك يا رب.
May God keep you safe.
هلق هذا البيت هو بيتكم؟
Now, this house is your house?
تمام.
Correct.
بتخلينا ندخل شوي نمشي هون نتعرف على معالمه؟
Will you let us enter a bit, walk around here, and explore
its features?
إيه تفضل.
Yes, go ahead.
هلق نحن صرنا في في وسط البيت الآن خلينا نقول.
Now we are in the middle of the house right now, let's say.
إيه.
Yes.
احكي لي عن هالبيت.
Tell me about this house.
هالبيت صاير بالأصل لمين؟
This house originally belongs to whom?
لأجدادنا يعني.
To our ancestors, I mean.
أجدادكم، إنتو من بيت مين؟
Your ancestors, you are from whose family?
من بيت حاج حميد... حاج حميد عثمان.
From the family of Haj Hameed... Haj Hameed Othman.
حاج حميد عثمان. أصلكم من وين؟
Haj Hameed Othman. Where are you originally from?
الأصل أصل من أورفة سروج.
The origin, the origin is from Urfa, Suruc.
من أورفة.
From Urfa.
من سروج.
From Suruc.
تمام. قد إيش عمر هالبيت؟
Great. How old is this house?
عمره مئتين وخمسين سنة.
It is 250 years old.
مئتين وخمسين سنة. شو كان استخدامه؟
250 years. What was its use?
يعني ايش كان يستخدم؟ بيت سكن فقط ولا شو؟
I mean, what was it used for? Just a residential house or
what?
بيت سكن، إيه بيت سكن، هون كان غرف قديمة للدواب ولـ...
A residential house, yes, a residential house. Here were old
rooms for livestock and for...
مطبخ طويل عريض، هون كان في جب هون موجود، جب هون موجود.
A long and wide kitchen, here there was a well here, a well
is located here.
جب يعني؟
Well means?
جب للمي لتجميع المي، جمع المي، أيوة.
A well for water, for collecting water, collecting water,
yeah.
هلق هذا البيت كان بيت آغا مثلا؟
Now, was this house the house of an Agha, for example?
والله جدي الرابع آغا، إيه عثمان آغا.
Well, my great-great-grandfather was an Agha, yes, Othman
Agha.
عثمان آغا كان.
It was Othman Agha.
كان آغا إيه.
He was an Agha, yes.
يعني هون في قلتي لي مطبخ كبير، لافت نظري المطبخ كبير.
I mean, here you told me there is a large kitchen, the large
kitchen caught my attention.
وهديك غرف ايش اللي جوه؟
Yes.
And what are those rooms inside?
هي غرف كان عمارة تقريبا خمستاشر متر، قنطرة وما قنطرة. نحن
جددناها غيرناها.
These rooms were an architecture of about fifteen meters, an
arch and what not. We renewed it and changed it.
غرف وحدة كانت؟
Was it a single room?
كانت غرفة وحدة إيه.
It was a single room, yes.
تستخدم للاستقبال وتستخدم للنوم؟
Used for reception and for sleeping?
للضيوف وللاستقبال تمام.
For guests and for reception, exactly.
طيب وهذا البناء؟
Okay, and this building?
هون كلها كان غرف هون بطول هيك بس هون كان جبة، هون كلها غرف
إيه.
Here, it was all rooms along here, but here there was a
well, here were all rooms, yes.
أيوة. يعني هذا هلا انتو هذا مجدد تجديد هيك.
I see. So this now, you've renewed it like this.
تجديد، نحن جددناه.
Renewal, we renewed it.
أما الحجر الأصلي قديم.
But the original stone is old.
قديم إيه.
Old, yes.
هون ايش في؟
What is here?
هون غرفة الكبيرة للوالد، غرفة كبيرة للضيوف هلا حاليا وغرفة
صغيرة كمان.
Here is the large room for my father, a large room for
guests right now, and a small room as well.
كمان لضيوف.
Also for guests.
إيه.
Yes.
ايش كان سابقا هون هي الغرفة الكبيرة تبع الوالد شو كانت؟
What was it previously here, this large room of your father,
what was it?
غرفة جدي يستقبل فيها الضيوف.
My grandfather's room, where he used to receive guests.
أه المضافة.
Ah, the guesthouse.
المضافة إيه المضافة.
The guesthouse, yes, the guesthouse.
أيوة.
I see.
قد إيش مساحة هالبيت؟
What is the area of this house?
شي ستمية متر.
About six hundred meters.
ستمية!
Six hundred!
إيه ما شاء الله.
Yes, God willing.
ما شاء الله.
God willing.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
في قطط كثير عندكم شو القصة؟
There are many cats here, what's the story?
الوالد بيحب القطط.
My father loves cats.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
عمو شلونك؟ شلون صحتك؟
Uncle, how are you? How is your health?
يا هلا. الحمد لله.
Welcome. Thank God.
هيدي الغرفة... يعني تراثية، بقيت على وضعها.
This room... is a heritage room, it remained in its original
state.
إي والله. هذا السقف خشب.
Yes, indeed. This ceiling is wooden.
هذا السقف خشب.
This ceiling is wooden.
خشب إيوا. نحن ما عدلنا فيه، كان في، عدلنا فيه على الخفيف.
Wood, yes. We didn't modify it, there was... we modified it
slightly.
شرف.
Please come in.
على الخفيف يعني، نحن الشباب، جينا عدلنا فيه.
Just slightly. We, the youth, came and modified it.
الأول كان فيه كله خشب، يعني مشان يحطوا صحونة وما صحونة.
At first, it was all wood, I mean, so they could put plates
and stuff.
رفوف، إيوا.
Shelves.
Shelves, yes.
وهي الشبابيك، نمط الشبابيك اللي كنت عم تحكي لي عليها هنيك.
And these windows, the style of windows you were telling me
about over there.
تمام، شبابيك العالية.
Exactly, the high windows.
هون كانت المضافة.
Here was the guest room.
هوني كانت المضافة، يبركوا يتطلعوا عالشارع.
Here was the guest room, they would sit and look at the
street.
هون كانت المضافة.
Here was the guest room.
إيوا، يجي هواء، هواء نظيف، وهذا هو.
Yes, fresh air would come in, and that's it.
هذا مع عمارنا القديم، يعني عمره يمكن عمر أبوي يمكن.
This is from our old buildings, I mean, it might be as old
as my father.
من عمر الوالد، تحية للغرفة.
As old as your father, greetings to the room.
الوالد تولد 37.
My father was born in '37.
هي الغرفة معناها انبنت حديثاً يعني؟ البيت 250 سنة، هون حديث.
Does this mean this room was built recently? The house is
250 years old, this is recent.
إيوا، هون حديث. هداك قديم.
Yes, here it's recent. That one is old.
هون حديث. هداك قديم.
Here it's recent. That one is old.
إيوا، هذا عمره 80، 85 سنة.
Yes, this is 80, 85 years old.
تمام، تمام.
That one is 250.
Exactly, exactly.
الله يعطيكم العافية، شكراً إلك.
May God give you health, thank you.
الله يعافيك. تفضلوا، نشربكم ونغديكم. هيك ما بيصير. والله.
May God give you health too. Please come in, let's offer you
something to drink and eat. You can't just leave. Really.
الله يرزقكم، والله إنكم مخبورين متل ما بيقولوا، الله يكرمكم.
كريمين والله.
May God bless you. You are truly well-known for your
hospitality as they say. May God honor you. You are
generous, by God.
تسلم، الله يخلي لنا ياكم ويحميكم يا رب.
Thank you, may God keep you and protect you.
الله يسلمك. الله يعطيك العافية يا عمو.
May God keep you. May God give you health, uncle.
يا هلا وسهلا. سلامات.
You are very welcome. Goodbye.
بالرغم من الأهمية الكبيرة لقرية جويق كونها تقع شمال غرب
عفرين مباشرة...
Despite the great importance of the village of Juwayq, being
located directly northwest of Afrin...
لكن لم نعرف تاريخ محدد لسكن الإنسان في هذه القرية.
...we do not know a specific date for human habitation in
this village.
لكن الثابت أن سكانها الأصليين سكنوا في المغر الموجودة خلفنا
في هذا الوادي.
But what is certain is that its original inhabitants lived
in the caves located behind us in this valley.
للحديث عن تاريخ جويق يسرنا أن يكون معنا العم عبد الكريم ملا
محمد...
To talk about the history of Juwayq, we are pleased to have
with us Uncle Abdul Karim Mulla Muhammad...
أحد أكبر الرجال الموجودين في هذه القرية والذي يهتم بتاريخها.
...one of the oldest men in this village who is interested
in its history.
يعطيك العافية يا عمي.
May God give you health, uncle.
أهلاً وسهلاً، أهلاً وسهلاً شرفتوا.
Welcome, welcome, you honor us.
الله يزيدك شرف يا رب.
May God increase your honor.
هلق حسب معلوماتك عمي عبد الكريم، يعني هالقرية شقد عمرها؟
Now, according to your information, Uncle Abdul Karim, how
old is this village?
الجد اللي جاي وساكن بهالمغر...
The grandfather who came and lived in these caves...
خلينا نمشي شوي، تفضل.
Let's walk a bit, please.
اللي ساكن بهالمغر بين 405 سنة مات أو 6 سنوات.
The one who lived in these caves, he died 405 or 406 years
ago.
جدكم أنتو؟
Your grandfather?
جدنا، ملا عمر، جاي من تركيا.
Our grandfather, Mulla Omar, came from Turkey.
من قضاء بيسني تابعة لعنتاب، اسم الضيعة حج سامة.
From the district of Besni, which belongs to Antep, the
village is called Haj Sama.
لما كانت على زمن الدولة العثمانية، لما كانت هي المناطق كلها
عربية يعني.
When it was during the Ottoman Empire, when all these areas
were Arab.
عربية بس إجوا لهون سكنوا...
Arab, but they came here and settled...
يعني تالت بيت إجا على هالقرية.
I mean, his was the third family to come to this village.
أنتو، تالت بيت.
You, the third family.
تالت بيت، نعم.
The third family, yes.
بيت عمارة أقدم مننا، وبيت الناصر أقدم مننا.
The Amara family is older than us, and the Nasser family is
older than us.
وتالت بيت إجا جدنا، برك بهالمغر هاديكي.
And the third family was our grandfather, he settled in
those caves over there.
بيت عمارة وبيت ناصر كمان سكنوا في المغر؟
The Amara and Nasser families also lived in the caves?
بالمغر. لحد الآن في مغر تبع بيت عمارة وفي تبع الناصر كمان
يعني.
In the caves. Until now, there are caves belonging to the
Amara family, and some for the Nasser family too.
طيب هلق عمو أنت قد إيش عمرك؟
So now, uncle, how old are you?
عمري، تولد 35، لكن ما خادم عسكرية...
My age, I was born in '35, but I didn't serve in the
military...
عمري يعني 86، الحمد لله رضيان بعمري ورضيان من الله سبحانه
وتعالى الحمد لله يعني.
So my age is 86. Thank God, I am satisfied with my age and
satisfied with God Almighty, thank God.
العمر كله، العمر كله.
May you live a long life, a long life.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you.
أنت عم تقول من 405 أو 406 سنوات جدكم إجا لهون، يعني شلون
عرفت هالموضوع؟
You are saying that 405 or 406 years ago your grandfather
came here. How did you know about this?
سألنا يعني، يعني الواحد لازم يسأل، من وين جاية؟ مين جده؟
كنيته إيشو؟
We asked, I mean, one must ask, where is he from? Who is his
grandfather? What is his surname?
يعني لازم الواحد يسأل لحتى ما يضيع يعني، ما يضيع.
One must ask so he doesn't get lost, so he doesn't get lost.
كنا بنسأل، مثلاً جدي كان عم بيقول لي جدنا فلان، جدنا فلان،
تعلمنا منه، يعني أخدنا الفكرة منه يعني.
We used to ask, for example, my grandfather used to tell me
our grandfather is so-and-so, our grandfather is so-and-so.
We learned from him, we took the idea from him.
طيب بعدكم مين إجا؟
So who came after you?
بعدنا... عائلات على كل حال.
After us... families, anyway.
في بيت، هن قراكيجي بيقولوا له، بيت حاج حميد هدول.
There is a family, they call them Qarakiji, the Haj Hamid
family.
في بيت حمدود هون، عائلات يعني.
There is the Hamdoud family here, families, you know.
من وين إجوا؟
Where did they come from?
هني بيعرفوا.
They would know.
هني بيعرفوا، بعد منا إجوا يعني.
They would know, they came after us.
بعض منكم. طيب قبل ما أسأل يعني المكونات اللي هون...
Some of you. Well, before I ask about the communities
here...
بدي أعرف إيمت انبنى أول بيت هون؟ بعد إيمت الناس بدأت تعمر؟
طلعت من المغر وصارت تعمر؟
I want to know when the first house was built here? When did
people start building? They left the caves and started
building?
بعد انجمعوا هدول، سكنوا بالمغر مشان ما يجي لهم بالليل حدا
يفتح بيتهم أو شي يعني، وحوش أو يعني، قطاع طرق، أيوة.
After these gathered, they lived in the caves so that no one
would come at night and open their house or something...
wild animals, or bandits, yes.
بعد ما صار شوية ضيعة يعني، شوي كم بيت صاروا... طلعوا من
المغر وعمروا.
After it became somewhat a village, you know, a few
houses... they came out of the caves and built.
بعد ما اتجمعوا كلهم.
After they all gathered.
هي العمارة هي، وهنيكي، صايرين...
This building, and over there, they became...
قداموا...
In front of...
يعني ظهر البيوت صاير ببعضهم يعني مشان هدول يحموا بعض، ظهر
البيوت في بعض، يا سلام.
I mean, the backs of the houses are connected to each other,
so they can protect each other. The backs of the houses are
together, amazing.
طلعوا معناها من المغر، كانوا يحتموا في المغر، يعيشوا في
المغر، ولما اتجمعوا كلهم طلعوا سكنوا وعمروا بيوت هون.
So they came out of the caves, they used to take shelter in
the caves, live in the caves, and when they all gathered,
they came out, settled, and built houses here.
نعم.
Yes.
طيب هلق بدي تحكي لي عمي، يعني المكونات الاجتماعية هون، في
كرد وفي عرب وفي تركمان، احكي لي عنهم.
Okay, now I want you to tell me, uncle, about the social
communities here. There are Kurds, Arabs, and Turkmen. Tell
me about them.
صايرين متلنا يعني، مو عم نعيش مع بعضنا بقرية وحدة، ببيئة
وحدة... صاروا متل بعضنا يعني.
They became like us, I mean, aren't we living together in
one village, in one environment... they became like us.
ضاعت التفاصيل.
The differences disappeared.
لا، يعني لا فرق بين عربي أو أعجمي إلا بالتقوى يعني.
No, I mean, there is no difference between an Arab and a
non-Arab except in piety.
تمام.
Exactly.
الحمد لله.
Thank God.
إي بس يعني مين؟ احكي لي متلاً بيت ناصر وبيت عمارة شو هدول؟
Yes, but who? Tell me, for example, the Nasser family and
the Amara family, what are they?
أكراد.
Kurds.
بيت ناصر وبيت عمارة؟
The Nasser family and the Amara family?
بيت ناصر عم بيقولوا، قدام النعيم، قرابتنا شواخ البرسان.
The Nasser family, they say, are in front of Al-Na'im, our
relatives are Shawakh Al-Bursan.
بيت ناصر عرب يعني معناها؟
The Nasser family are Arabs, then?
عم بيقولوا عرب يعني، بيت ناصر.
They say they are Arabs, the Nasser family.
وبيت عمارة؟
And the Amara family?
بيت عمارة أكراد يعني.
The Amara family are Kurds.
أكراد.
Kurds.
وبيت ملا عمر؟
And the Mulla Omar family?
أكراد.
Kurds.
أكراد. بيت حسن وبيت عز الدين؟
Kurds. The Hassan family and the Izz al-Din family?
بيت حسن، بيت واحد إجا أبوهم من تركيا، صار إمام الجامع عنا،
وأخدت وحدة من بيت عز الدين هدول من قرايبهم، وصاروا يساووا
مجوز...
The Hassan family, it was one family whose father came from
Turkey. He became the imam of the mosque here, and took a
wife from the Izz al-Din family, from their relatives, and
they started getting married...
كان إمام الجامع يعني.
He was the imam of the mosque.
بيت عز الدين عرب ولا نعيم ولا؟
Is the Izz al-Din family Arab, or Na'im, or...?
لا لا، مو نعيم لا، كمان جايين من تركيا هنن.
No, no, not Na'im, no, they also came from Turkey.
طيب هلق تركيا كانت حدود مفتوحة لما إجوا لهون، عم تقول أنت عم
تحكي من 400، 500 سنة...
Okay, now, Turkey had open borders when they came here. You
are talking about 400, 500 years ago...
405، 6 سنوات يعني.
405, 406 years, I mean.
هادا أقرب، مو أقرب، هادا تاريخكم أنتو. أما بيت ناصر وبيت
عمارة أقدم منكم.
This is closer... not closer, this is your history. But the
Nasser family and the Amara family are older than you.
إي نعم.
Yes, indeed.
Isn't that right?
إي نعم.
Yes, indeed.
عملياً تاريخياً، سكان هالضيعة كلهم... خلينا نمشي شوي... سكان
هالضيعة اللي هن عرب وكرد وتركمان كيف كانت علاقاتهم؟
Practically, historically, the inhabitants of this village
all... let's walk a bit... the inhabitants of this village
who are Arabs, Kurds, and Turkmen, how were their
relationships?
علاقاتهم منيح.
Their relationships were good.
كيف؟
How?
يعني كان بيعاونوا بعضهم، بيعطوا لبعضهم متلاً، يجوزوا من
بعضهم مشان يصير قربة يعني.
I mean, they used to help each other, give to each other,
for example, marry from each other to become relatives.
مشان قربة يعني، مو بركين بفرد ضيعة.
To become relatives, not just sitting in the same village.
نعم، مشان يصير قربة يعني بيناتهم.
Yes, to become relatives among themselves.
معناها أخدوا وأعطوا من بعض.
So they intermarried and exchanged.
لكان.
Of course.
إيش بيحكوا كلياتهم أي لغة هون؟
What language do they all speak here?
هون بيحكوا أي لغة، عربي، كردي؟
What language do they speak here, Arabic, Kurdish?
كردية، الكردية.
Kurdish, Kurdish.
الكل أكراد بيحكوا؟
Do all of them speak Kurdish?
كله أكراد.
All are Kurds.
ما بيحكوا عربي؟
They don't speak Arabic?
لا ما في.
No, there isn't.
ما بيحكوا عربي نهائياً؟
They don't speak Arabic at all?
هلق في ناس مثلاً بلكي فيها عرب بيحكوا عربي مع بعضهم.
Now there are people, for example, maybe there are Arabs who
speak Arabic with each other.
أما بيننا بيحكوا بكردي.
But among us, they speak Kurdish.
أه، يعني أهل القرية بيتداولوا بين بعضهم اللغة الكردية.
Oh, so the people of the village use the Kurdish language
among themselves.
إي لكان.
Yes, of course.
أما متلاً العرب بيحكوا عربي والكرد بيحكوا كردي والتركمان
تركماني.
But, for example, the Arabs speak Arabic, the Kurds speak
Kurdish, and the Turkmen speak Turkmen.
لكان في بيتهم يعني هيك يعني.
Of course, in their homes, I mean, like that.
تمام، تمام.
Exactly, exactly.
أيضاً كمان تاريخياً، يعني اللي اشتغلوا فيه، إيش كانوا
يشتغلوا؟
Also, historically, I mean, what they worked in, what did
they use to work in?
هي نوقف هون عمو. بالفلاحة.
Let's stop here, uncle. In farming.
بالفلاحة.
In farming.
شرف شرف تفضل.
Please come here.
تاريخياً كانوا يشتغلوا بالفلاحة بالزراعة يعني؟
Historically, they used to work in farming, in agriculture?
بالزراعة، أول ما كان في شيء. يا غنامة، يا إما عنده غنم، يا
إما بيشتغلوا بالزراعة.
In agriculture, at first there was nothing else. Either
shepherds, having sheep, or they worked in agriculture.
بالزراعة. يزرعوا هالحنطة وما حنطة وكروم عنب...
In agriculture. They would plant wheat and stuff, and
vineyards...
وما كان في زيتونات. أنا بصلت، ما كان في زيتونات بهالضيعة هي.
And there were no olive trees. As far as I can remember,
there were no olive trees in this village.
كان كله كروم عنب يعني؟
It was all vineyards?
كان كله كروم عنب، يعني.
It was all vineyards, yeah.
عمي هلق بسألك سؤال، عين ديبة اللي صايرة شرق الضيعة...
Uncle, let me ask you a question. Ayn Diba, which is east of
the village...
نعم.
Yes.
إيشو أهميتها للضيعة؟
What is its importance to the village?
منيح، في نبعة، الضيعة بتستفيد منه، من هالماء يعني.
It's good, there is a spring, the village benefits from it,
from this water.
كان في تلات طواحين تحت هالماء، بيشغلوا الطاحون يعني.
There were three mills under this water, they would operate
the mill.
طاحونة طحين؟
A flour mill?
طاحونة طحين لكان، عالماء كان.
A flour mill, of course, it ran on water.
إيوا.
Yes.
يعني الناس تشرب منا، وتسقي أراضيها؟
So people would drink from it, and irrigate their lands?
تسقي أراضيها وهم...
Irrigate their lands and also...
بيشغلوا تلات طواحين كمان؟ طاحونات يعني؟
And run three mills too? Mills, I mean?
إيوا.
Yes.
بقي سؤال واحد.
One question remains.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
قبل ما نبدأ التصوير معك، كنت عم تحكي لي إنه أولي الناس كانت
تساعد مع بعض في الحصاد، وعلى الندي وما ندي، احكي لي هالقصة.
Before we started filming with you, you were telling me that
in the past, people used to help each other in the harvest,
and with the 'Nedeh' and things like that. Tell me this
story.
لأنه واحد سألني... لما بالتعزية على كل حال، تطلع علي، فيني
قال أنت بالعمر يعني أكبر...
Because someone asked me... when we were at a condolence
gathering anyway, he looked at me, and said, you are the
oldest in age...
احكي لنا عالتاريخ الأولي شلون، وهلق شلون.
Tell us about the history in the past, how it was, and how
it is now.
قلت له أولي، كان كله مزارعين يعني، عم بيعاونوا بعضهم يعني،
عالحصاد، عالدراسة تبع الحنطة، جرجر بيقولوا له...
I told him, in the past, everyone was a farmer, they used to
help each other, with the harvest, threshing the wheat, with
a thresher they call it...
يعاونوا بعضهم. قلت له كنا يعني صغار، بين الختيارية، لواحد
منا أكبر منا بسنتين كنا بنقوم على حيلنا، في محل...
They helped each other. I told him we were young among the
elders, for someone just two years older than us, we would
stand up, if there was a place...
بس احتراماً لهالكبير يعني.
Just out of respect for the elder.
احتراماً للموجود.
Out of respect for who's present.
احتراما للكبير كنا نقوم، يبرك الكبير بعدين كنا نبرك.
Out of respect, yes.
Out of respect for the elders, we used to stand up, the
elder would sit down, then we would sit.
مثلا بين هالضيعة، بنات، نسوان كانوا باركين، منغير كنا طريقنا
عليهم.
For example, in this village, if girls or women were
sitting, we used to change our path away from them.
مشان ما تمروا قدامهم.
So you wouldn't pass in front of them.
أيوة.
Yes.
وكنتوا تتساعدوا أيضا بالحصاد مثل ما قلتلي.
And you also used to help each other with the harvest, as
you told me.
بكلشي. كنا منشوف بعضنا مثلا تم حصاد فلان ما ينحصد إلا في
الندا.
In everything. We used to look out for each other, for
instance, someone's harvest would only be reaped in the
morning dew.
منشوف بعضنا شباب اللي بالضيعة، منشوف بعضنا كم واحد، عشرة
خمستعش،
We would see each other, the young men of the village, we
would see how many we were, ten or fifteen,
بوجه الصبح بنكون نحنا بين الحصاد عم نحصده بدون مقابل يعني.
And at the break of dawn, we would be amidst the harvest,
harvesting it without any compensation.
بدون مقابل، بدون ما تقولوا له.
Without compensation, without even telling him.
لكا، لكا، لكا.
Of course, of course, of course.
لصاحب الرزق.
To the owner of the crop.
ما شاء الله. أخلاق رائعة.
Of course.
Mashallah. Wonderful morals.
الحمد لله.
Thank God.
الحمد لله، أهلا وسهلا. الله يطول عمرك.
Thank God, welcome. May God give you a long life.
شرفتونا، أهلا وسهلا.
You have honored us, welcome.
عذبناك معنا شوي.
We bothered you a little bit with us.
أهلا وسهلا، أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome, welcome.
على راسي عمي أبو عبدو.
On my head, uncle Abu Abdo.
أهلا وسهلا، أهلا وسهلا، أهلين.
Welcome, welcome, welcome.
هلا بهالفقرة رح نطلع معكم جولة بالسيارة في قلب الضيعة.
Now in this segment, we will take you on a car tour in the
heart of the village.
لاحظوا الضيعة مقسومة قسمين، شمالي وجنوبي.
Notice how the village is divided into two parts, northern
and southern.
الوادي اللي كان فيه مجرى مائي سابقا قاسم الضيعة لقسمين.
The valley, which previously had a water stream, divides the
village into two parts.
هذا هو الوادي، الآن عم يتم بناء جدار لحتى يمنع السيل إنه
يجرف الطريق.
This is the valley, a wall is currently being built to
prevent the flood from washing away the road.
وهون في جسر محل ما نحنا الآن موجودين.
And here there is a bridge where we are currently located.
لاحظوا على يساري الآن الوادي كيف مزروع بأشجار الرمان.
Notice on my left now how the valley is planted with
pomegranate trees.
الضيعة جميلة جدا وساحرة حقيقة.
The village is very beautiful and truly charming.
واضح فيها العراقة.
Its antiquity is clear.
نحنا الآن في القسم الجنوبي.
We are now in the southern section.
لاحظوا البيوت كيف عم تتصاعد شوي شوي فوق الهضبة.
Notice how the houses are gradually climbing up the hill.
سواء على القسم اليميني اللي شايفينه الآن يعني شمالا أو على
القسم الجنوبي.
Whether on the right section that you see now, meaning the
north, or on the southern section.
الأبنية عم تتصاعد لفوق أعلى الهضبة.
The buildings are climbing up to the top of the hill.
بيميز القرية أشجار المظلة الموجودة الآن واللي كلها مقصوصة
بسبب فصل الشتاء والخريف، الآن يتم تقليمها.
The village is distinguished by the umbrella trees currently
present, which are all cut due to the winter and autumn
seasons, they are being pruned now.
منظر بديع وجميل لأشجار المظلة. كتير حلوة.
A magnificent and beautiful sight of the umbrella trees.
Very nice.
هون المدرسة على يساري، وأبنية قديمة.
Here is the school on my left, and old buildings.
هذا الطريق اللي أمامي الآن هو الطريق اللي بيؤدي إلى قرية
داركير واللي واقعة غربي جويق.
This road in front of me now is the road that leads to the
village of Dargir, which is located west of Jweq.
لاحظوا هذا هو الوادي العميق، واللي أحيانا بتمشي فيه المي
بسبب السيول اللي جاية من جهة داركير.
Notice this is the deep valley, in which water sometimes
flows due to floods coming from the direction of Dargir.
وادي عميق متل مو واضح.
A deep valley, as is clear.
بعض الخيام لمهجرين من مناطق سورية مختلفة على يسارنا في أراضي
جويق.
Some tents of displaced people from different Syrian regions
on our left in the lands of Jweq.
أمامنا بالضبط الآن الوادي.
Right in front of us now is the valley.
لاحظوا هذا الوادي السحيق، واللي فيه المغر الأساسية اللي
سكنوا فيها سكان الضيعة الأوائل لما أجوا لهون.
Notice this deep valley, which contains the main caves where
the first inhabitants of the village lived when they came
here.
طبعا الضيعة طبيعتها زراعية، تعتمد في الأساس على الزراعة
وتربية الحيوانات.
Of course, the nature of the village is agricultural, it
mainly relies on agriculture and animal husbandry.
على يميني الوادي، بدأ الآن شجر اللوز يفتح زهره.
To my right is the valley, the almond trees have now begun
to bloom.
الجياد بيستخدموها أهل الضيعة في الفلاحة ونقل الحطب، أمامنا.
Horses are used by the people of the village for farming and
transporting firewood, right in front of us.
طبعا طبيعة القرية كتير وعرة صراحة وصعبة.
Of course, the nature of the village is very rugged,
honestly, and difficult.
الآن صرنا في الحارة الشمالية، أو في الجزء الشمالي من القرية،
وصار على يميننا الوادي.
Now we are in the northern neighborhood, or in the northern
part of the village, and the valley is on our right.
يمكن هذا المشهد اللي أمامنا، الأغنام اللي عم ترعى، الكلاب،
ابن القرية الفلاح، بيلخص نمط حياة جويق كلها.
Perhaps this scene in front of us, the sheep grazing, the
dogs, the farmer villager, summarizes the lifestyle of all
of Jweq.
الطرق الملتوية تحت في أسفل الوادي، الربيع اللي بدأ يظهر الآن
في الفسح الترابية الموجودة بين البيوت.
The winding roads down at the bottom of the valley, the
spring that has begun to appear now in the dirt spaces
between the houses.
بتلخص سيرة أو حكاية جويق.
It summarizes the story or the tale of Jweq.
هلق رح نتابع معكم لأسفل الضيعة.
Now we will continue with you to the bottom of the village.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله.
And upon you be peace and the mercy of God.
بدي احكي معكم شوي.
I want to talk to you a little bit.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
And upon you be peace, the mercy of God, and His blessings.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك يا رب.
May God give you health, Lord.
نتعرف عليكم شوي.
Let's get to know you a bit.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
الحمد لله.
How are you?
Praise be to God.
الحمد لله على سلامتكم.
Thank God for your safety.
نتعرف عليكم.
May God keep you safe.
Let's get to know you.
أهلاً وسهلاً، والله أنا عزيز أبو محمد.
Welcome, I am Aziz Abu Mohammed.
يا هلا ومية مرحبا، من وين؟
Welcome and a hundred welcomes, where from?
من جرجناز.
From Jarjnaz.
من جرجناز. وحضرتك؟
From Jarjnaz. And you?
محمد الإبراهيم محمد، من صهيان بإدلب.
Mohammed Al-Ibrahim Mohammed, from Sahyan in Idlib.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم.
Welcome to you.
أبو ظهور.
Abu al-Duhur.
كانكم جيران؟
It seems you are neighbors?
والله يعني جيران نعم.
Well, yes, neighbors indeed.
إي جيران بعدين، ما ضل بعدين نفس الشي، الحمد لله نحنا جيران
بعدين.
Yes, we became neighbors later on, there's no difference
later on, thank God we are neighbors now.
إي والله.
Yes, by God.
وهالغنمات لمين؟ إلك ولا إله؟
And whose sheep are these? Yours or his?
لحجي.
For the Hajji.
لا ما عندي.
You don't have sheep?
No, I don't.
نعم إلي.
Yes, they are mine.
احكولي عن حياتكم أنتو...
Tell me about your life, you...
والله حياتنا الحمد لله على كل حال.
By God, our life, praise be to God in any case.
كمهجرين، شلون وضعكم؟
As displaced people, how is your situation?
والله وضعنا مع أهل الضيعة كويس ماشي الحال. الحمد لله، بس
واحد يريد بلاده يا أخي، أريح له.
By God, our situation with the village people is good, it's
okay. Praise be to God, but one wants his country, brother,
it's more comfortable for him.
إحنا القصة وما فيها نريد بلادنا. أرضنا وبيوتنا وأهلنا وكلها،
كل واحد صار ببلد.
True.
إحنا القصة وما فيها نريد بلادنا. أرضنا وبيوتنا وأهلنا وكلها،
كل واحد صار ببلد.
The whole story is that we want our country. Our land, our
homes, our families, and all, everyone is now in a different
country.
هذا اللي إحنا طالبينه.
Right.
This is what we are asking for.
احكيلي عن حياتكم هون، شلون عايشين؟
Tell me about your life here, how are you living?
حياتنا والله الحمد لله رب العالمين، يعني ماشي الحال. يعني ما
هي فوق فوق، نقول يعني إنه، بس التهجير هذا صعب عنا.
Our life, by God, praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds, I
mean, it's okay. I mean, it's not perfect to say that, but
this displacement is hard for us.
قصدي معتمدين على الزراعة، معتمدين على الحيوانات؟
I mean, do you rely on agriculture, do you rely on animals?
ما عندنا لا زراعة ولا عندنا شي والله.
We have neither agriculture nor anything, by God.
والله على ولادي بيشتغلوا برا وبيبعتولنا كم ورقة شاب خطية
عايشين من وراهم، نعجات هذول نبيع وناكل.
Except for the sheep?
والله على ولادي بيشتغلوا برا وبيبعتولنا كم ورقة شاب خطية
عايشين من وراهم، نعجات هذول نبيع وناكل.
By God, my children work abroad and send us a few bills,
poor youths, we live off them, and these ewes, we sell from
them and eat.
ما في عندنا شي.
Right.
We don't have anything.
الله يقويكم.
May God give you strength.
الحمد لله رب العالمين.
Praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds.
وإنت شلون حياتك؟ احكيلي عنك.
And you, how is your life? Tell me about yourself.
والله الحمد لله رب العالمين، في كم شجرة في هالجبل هيك عم
نعيش وراهم.
By God, praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds, there are a
few trees on this mountain that we live off.
ما في لا دجاجات ولا شي.
There are no chickens or anything.
تمام.
Right.
الحمد لله رب العالمين، عايشين وممشي الحال.
Praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds, we are living and
getting by.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
أهلين، مع السلامات.
Welcome.
Welcome, goodbye.
الله يعطيكم العافية، ومشكورين.
May God grant you success.
May God give you health, and thank you.
يا هلا ومية مرحبا.
Welcome and a hundred welcomes.
أهلين وسهلين.
Welcome.
رح نتابع جولتنا.
We will continue our tour.
لاحظوا زهر اللوز.
Notice the almond blossoms.
قديش جميل ببداية الربيع.
How beautiful it is at the beginning of spring.
القرية، بيميزها أيضا وجود كلاب حراسة للأهالي كتير.
The village is also distinguished by the presence of many
guard dogs for the residents.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
الله يعطيك العافية.
Peace and mercy.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك يا رب.
May God give you health, Lord.
ممكن أحكي معك؟
Can I talk to you?
تفضل.
Go ahead.
حصان أصيل هاد ولا شلون؟
Is this a purebred horse or what?
لا، مانه أصيل.
No, it's not a purebred.
وين كنت هيك؟
Where were you?
بالبيت.
At home.
عم تفلح هيك؟ كنت عم تفلح، إيش عم تفلح؟
You're farming like this? You were farming, what are you
farming?
فول.
Fava beans.
فول؟
Fava beans?
الله يعطيك العافية.
Yes.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
من الصبح لهلأ؟
From morning until now?
لا، من الصبح لبعد الظهر.
No, from morning until the afternoon.
من الصبح للظهر. وبعدين العصر بتفلح كمان؟
From morning to noon. And then in the late afternoon do you
farm too?
هلق حالياً لا.
Well, currently no.
لا؟ بس من الصبح للظهر. عم تفلح بالأجرة؟
No? Just from morning to noon. Are you farming for a wage?
إي.
Yes.
شقد الدونم؟
How much per dunam?
والله عم نفلح باليومية.
By God, we farm by the daily wage.
شقد؟
How much?
20 ليرة؟
20.
20 liras?
20 ألف.
20 thousand.
20 ألف. الله يعطيك العافية. إنت من وين؟
20 thousand. May God give you health. Where are you from?
من عنجارة، يا أهلاً وسهلاً فيك، مهجر لهون.
From Anjara.
From Anjara, welcome to you, displaced here.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
هلق هاد الوادي هون، الوادي وكأنه بيرعوا فيه الأغنام، بيزرعوه
يعني للمرعى مو هيك؟
Now this valley here, it's as if sheep graze in it, they
plant it for pasture, isn't that so?
إي، هذاك الزرع.
Yes, that is the planting.
ضيعة كتير حلوة، كتير جميلة.
A very nice village, very beautiful.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
الله يسلمك.
Thank you.
May God keep you safe.
بهالفقرة رح نزور ست من ستات جويق المميزة.
In this segment, we will visit one of the distinguished
ladies of Jweq.
إم سوار، شخصية مميزة بجويق.
Um Siwar, a distinguished personality in Jweq.
تعتمد على حالها برعاية أرضها وأيضا العناية بحيواناتها لتربي
أسرتها الصغيرة هون.
She relies on herself in tending her land and also caring
for her animals to raise her small family here.
رح ندخل لعندها نتعرف على عوالم حياتها البسيطة ونتعرف أيضا
كيف رح تطبخلنا اللبنية المشهورة بهالقرية.
We will go inside to her, get to know her simple lifestyle,
and also learn how she will cook us the labaniyeh famous in
this village.
تفضلوا معنا.
Please come with us.
إم سوار؟
Um Siwar?
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام. شلونك؟
And upon you be peace. How are you?
الحمد لله، تفضلوا.
Praise be to God, please come in.
يلا.
Let's go.
أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
يا رب.
Oh Lord.
يا أم سوار، شرفي معي.
Ya Um Siwar, please come with me.
أول شيء بدي تعرفي الناس عليكي.
First of all, I want you to introduce yourself to the
people.
ع الكاميرا خلي وجهك هيك. عرفي الناس عليكي، مين أم سوار؟
Keep your face towards the camera like this. Introduce
yourself to the people. Who is Um Siwar?
أم سوار امرأة بسيطة، متواضعة.
Um Siwar is a simple, humble woman.
ساكنة بالضيعة، بحالها، محترمة.
Living in the village, minding her own business, respectful.
والنعم، وبتدبر أمور عائلتها الصغار...
Indeed, and you manage the affairs of your small family...
بتدبر أمور عائلتها بذاتها، بنفسها.
She manages her family's affairs on her own, by herself.
بتروحي ع الأرض، بتشوفي الحيوانات وكذا...
You go to the land, check on the animals, and so on...
أكيد، أكيد.
Sure, sure.
فرجينا الحيوانات اللي عندك.
Show us the animals you have.
عندي عنزتين...
I have two goats...
لحظة، شو في عندك؟
Wait, what do you have?
عندي بس عنزتين، من شي أسبوع ولدوا.
I only have two goats; they gave birth about a week ago.
ولدوا؟ شو ولدوا؟ اشرحي لنا هون.
Gave birth? What did they give birth to? Explain to us here.
ولدوا تنين أنثى وتنين ذكر.
They gave birth to two females and two males.
يعني جديات وصخلات.
Meaning male and female kids.
إيه الصخلات عندي بعد يومين قامت وحدة ميتة.
Yes, as for the female kids, after two days, one was found
dead.
سلامتك، البقية بأمرك. تمام، وشو في عندك هون كمان؟
I'm sorry to hear that, may the others live long. Alright,
and what else do you have here?
هي جحشة.
This is a female donkey.
حمارة يعني.
A donkey, I see.
إيه، هي بتلزمني للشغل وقت الزيتون.
Yes, I need her for work during the olive season.
أو حطب، بنجيبه حطب بنروح فيها ع الأرض تبع الزيتون.
Or for firewood, we use her to bring firewood, we go with
her to the olive field.
هاد الحطب إنتي جبتيه؟
Did you bring this firewood?
إيه هاد كله نقلته من الزيتون، أرض جيراننا هون كانوا كله
مكسحين أرضهم.
Yes, I transported all of this from the olive field, our
neighbors' land here, they had pruned their land.
وكله هيك بساويه حزم، بربطه وبشحطه شحط.
I make them all into bundles, tie them up, and drag them all
the way.
إنتي؟
You?
إيه والله.
Yes, I swear.
وهاد؟ هاد؟
And this? This?
وهاد كمان كنت أعبي كيس، آخد معي كيس أبيض سماد.
And for this too, I used to fill a bag, I'd take a white bag
of fertilizer with me.
متل هاد الكيس، آخد معي وقت بروح بسرح بالعنزات، بعبي الكيس
وبجيب معي.
Like this bag. I take it with me when I go to graze the
goats, I fill the bag and bring it with me.
هون شو في عندك كمان؟ حمام، جينا، شو في عندك؟
What else do you have here? A bathroom, we came here, what
do you have?
لا، دجاجات، هون قن للدجاج.
No, chickens, this is a chicken coop.
دجاجات. وشو في عندك أرض؟ عندك زيتونات، عندك شي؟
Chickens. And what land do you have? Do you have olive
trees, do you have anything?
والله ما في غير أرض الورثة تبع عمي، يعني ولاده، خلخالي،
زيتون خلخالي.
I swear there's only the inherited land of my uncle, I mean
his children, Khalkhali, Khalkhali olives.
أستاذ خلخالي. وإنتي بتعتني فيها، بتروحي وبترجعي...
Mr. Khalkhali. And you take care of it, you go and come
back...
إيه، إيه.
Yes, yes.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health.
May God give you health too.
يعني إنتي معتمدة ع الأرض وع الحيوانات تبعك وعايشة منهم.
So you rely on the land and your animals, and make a living
from them.
أكيد، إيه.
Certainly, yes.
طيب، هلق إنتي رح تفرجينا هاد البيت قديش عمره.
Alright, now you're going to show us how old this house is.
خلينا ندخل ع بيتك شوي لهون هيك بس من برا نشوفه من برا.
Let's enter your house a bit here, just from the outside,
let's see it from the outside.
هاد بيتك.
This is your house.
إيه.
Yes.
منفصل عن مكان الحيوانات.
Separated from the animals' place.
أكيد إيه، هي حوش لحالها.
Certainly yes, this is a separate yard.
هاد شقد عمره هالبيت؟
How old is this house?
مواليد من وقت الـ 1971.
It dates back to 1971.
واحد وسبعين. بس شوي لو سمحتي...
Seventy-one. Just a moment, please...
أيوا، واحد وسبعين. يعني واحد وسبعين عمره صار خمسين سنة.
Yes, seventy-one. Meaning from seventy-one, it's now fifty
years old.
هلق إنتي رح تفرجينا... رح ندخل ع المطبخ هيك وتفرجينا كيف
تطبخي اللبنية.
Now you're going to show us... we will enter the kitchen and
you'll show us how you cook Labaniye.
ماشي.
Okay.
تفضلي.
Please go ahead.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
تفضلي، يلا شعلي النار.
Go ahead, let's light the fire.
تمام، هلق شو رح تسوي، احكي لي أول شي مكونات اللبنية من إيش؟
Alright, now what are you going to do, tell me first, what
are the ingredients of Labaniye?
مكونات اللبنية بتصير من اللبن، كيلوين لبن، مع كاسة رز.
The ingredients of Labaniye consist of yogurt, two kilos of
yogurt, with a cup of rice.
لبن... لبن غنم ولا بقر؟
Yogurt... sheep or cow's yogurt?
بفضل الغنم والـ...
Preferably sheep and...
الغنم.
Sheep.
الغنم والبقر، بس أنا عندي تبع المعزى، معزاتي.
Sheep and cow, but I have it from the goats, my goats.
المعزات، هاد لبن معز.
The goats, this is goat yogurt.
معز.
Goat.
بتروبيه ولا بتحطيه على وضعه؟
Do you ferment it or do you put it as is?
روبته.
I fermented it.
روبتيه يعني.
So you fermented it.
إيه بس روبته بس سميك، ما خففته، سمكته.
Yes, I fermented it, but it's thick, I didn't dilute it, I
made it thick.
طيب، غير؟
Alright, what else?
معو الرز.
With rice.
ع البارد ولا بتحطيه ع النار؟
Cold or do you put it on the fire?
لا لا ع البارد إيه الرز، ومعه لحمة.
No, no, cold, yes rice, and with it meat.
وبعدين راس توم، وملح بس، ونعناع.
And then a head of garlic, and just salt, and mint.
تفضلي.
Go ahead.
وبس بدنا نضل ندير اللبن مشان ما...
And we just have to keep stirring the yogurt so it
doesn't...
ما يفرط.
Doesn't curdle.
التوم هلق ما بينحط له؟
Is the garlic not added to it now?
لا، التوم واللحمة، هاد ملح.
No, the garlic and the meat, this is salt.
هاد ملح؟
Is this salt?
لا التوم ولا اللحمة بس يغلي اللبن.
Neither the garlic nor the meat, until the yogurt boils.
اللبن ما بينترك.
The yogurt shouldn't be left alone.
ليش؟
Why?
مشان ما يفرط، بس تركته بيفرط.
So it doesn't curdle, if I leave it, it will curdle.
مشان هيك هاد جهزته جنبي.
That's why I prepared this next to me.
إنتي بشكل دائم تطبخي ع النار؟
Do you constantly cook on the fire?
إيه.
Yes.
ع هدول، ع الحطب.
On these, on the firewood.
إيه الطبخات الكبيرة، أغلبية الأكل، الطبخ ع النار.
Yes, the large meals, most of the food, the cooking is on
the fire.
شقد ممكن تستمري هيك بهالشكل؟
How long might you continue like this?
للغلي.
Until it boils.
يعني تقريباً شي بتاكل عشر دقايق؟
So it takes roughly about ten minutes?
عشر دقايق ربع ساعة. عشر دقايق ربع ساعة بتاكل.
Ten minutes, a quarter of an hour. Ten minutes, a quarter of
an hour it takes.
لأنه الطنجرة نصها، لبين ما تغلي...
Because the pot is half full, until it boils...
بتاكل وقت.
It takes time.
بالشوبك هاد، اللبن بيطلع يعني الـ...
With this rolling pin, the yogurt comes out, I mean...
بتدير فيه اللبن أحسن.
You stir the yogurt with it better.
هلق ما بتحطي الرز لحتى يعني يغلي؟
Now, you don't add the rice until it boils?
لا، الرز معه مشان ينتقع، مشان ينفش بسرعة ينطبخ معه.
No, the rice is with it so it can soak, so it swells quickly
and cooks with it.
واللحمة؟
And the meat?
اللحمة بعدين، ايمتى ما كان بتصير اللحمة بعدين بس يطبخ اللبن.
The meat is for later, the meat can be added anytime later,
once the yogurt cooks.
بس يغلي هو والتوم، اللحمة والتوم سوا والنعناع.
Once it boils, it and the garlic, the meat and the garlic
together, and the mint.
يعني هلق بعد ما غلي اللبن بدنا نحط اللحمة؟
So now after the yogurt has boiled, we need to put the meat?
ما بحسن أذوق ملحه هلق لأنه أنا صايمة.
I can't taste its salt right now because I am fasting.
صايمة!
Fasting!
ما شاء الله عليكي، شو المناسبة؟
Fasting, yes.
Mashallah, what's the occasion?
لأنه دخلنا بشهر رجب.
Because we entered the month of Rajab.
الله يتقبل يا رب، الله يتقبل. إيش بيتاكل جنبها هي؟
May God accept it, oh Lord, may God accept it. What is eaten
next to this?
يا فريكة، يا برغل.
Either freekeh or bulgur.
يا فريكة يا برغل؟
Either freekeh or bulgur?
امم، حصراً.
Yes, exclusively.
حصراً؟ ايشو في أكلات كمان تانية هون مشهورة؟
Exclusively? What other dishes are famous here?
في الششبرك، البورانية، الكبة، السمبوسك.
There is shishbarak, boraniye, kibbeh, samosa.
يعني أكلات خلينا نقول ريفية على حلبية.
I see, dishes we could say are rural mixed with Aleppian.
أيوة.
Exactly.
يا ستي إفطار شهي إن شاء الله. والله يتقبل منك يا أم سوار.
Well ma'am, have a delicious Iftar, God willing. And may God
accept your fasting, Um Siwar.
الله يسلمك يا رب.
May God keep you safe, oh Lord.
الله يخليكي. السلام عليكم.
May God protect you. Peace be upon you.
مع السلامة أهلاً وسهلاً.
Goodbye, welcome.
الله يكرمكم.
May God honor you.
جمال الطبيعة بجويق هو الشيء المميز والملفت.
The beauty of nature in Jweq is what's special and eye-
catching.
حقيقة الخضار اللي عم يطلع الآن من قعر الوادي...
Truly, the greenery that is rising now from the bottom of
the valley...
اللي بيقسم الضيعة لقسمين باتجاه أعلى الهضبتين اللي انبنت
عليهم البيوت في الشمال والجنوب...
Which divides the village into two parts towards the top of
the two hills upon which the houses were built in the north
and the south...
عم يلون هالضيعة بلون جميل وبيعطيها طعم ونكهة كتير حلوة.
Is coloring this village with a beautiful color and giving
it a very sweet taste and flavor.
أيضاً الكرم اللي بيتميزوا فيه أهل هالقرية ملفت كتير للنظر.
Also, the generosity that the people of this village are
characterized by is very striking to the eye.
التعايش بينهم وبين المهجرين لهون من إدلب ومن حماة ومن حلب
ومن كل المناطق السورية...
The coexistence between them and the displaced people who
came here from Idlib, Hama, Aleppo, and from all the Syrian
regions...
أيضاً شيء ملفت وبيبشر بالخير إن شاء الله لتكون سوريا القادمة
لونها هاد اللون وطعمها هاد الطعم ونكهتها هيدي النكهة.
Is also something striking and brings good tidings, God
willing, that the future Syria will have this color, this
taste, and this flavor.
رح نكون معكم في الأسبوع القادم بجولة جديدة من منطقة سورية
أخرى حبيبة.
We will be with you next week on a new tour from another
beloved Syrian region.
لمتابعة برنامجنا تابعوا صفحة الفيس الخاصة بالقناة وأيضاً
موقعنا على الإنترنت حلب تودي تي في دوت نت.
To follow our program, follow the channel's Facebook page
and also our website halabtodaytv.net.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.